Johann Wentzel

HCI Researcher · Virtual and Augmented Reality · Accessibility

L 1 (403) 464 7217

→ hello@johannwentzel.ca

iohannwentzel.ca

Overview

I study ways to make spatial computing more accessible, using novel adaptations of familiar input devices. My research process involves qualitative methods and co-design, prototyping new spatial interfaces and interaction techniques, then deploying user studies to evaluate their usability. My thesis work explores improving VR's accessibility for people with motor disabilities by combining more familiar input devices (game controllers, mice, etc.) as an alternative to standard VR controllers. By focusing on the interplay between users' input devices and their surrounding context, my work enables AR/VR experiences that are more accessible to those with reduced mobility. I published several papers throughout my PhD and completed research internships at Meta, Microsoft, and Autodesk.

Recent research interests include:

AR/VR interface prototyping • multi-modal interfaces • gaze tracking • input remapping • generative AI for VR design • technology ethics • large language models • evaluating VR/AR UX • VR locomotion design

Education

University of Waterloo Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) - Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction), GPA: 96% Thesis: Bring-Your-Own Input: Context-Aware Multi-Modal Input for More Accessible VR Advisor: Daniel Vogel [website]	Waterloo, ON May 2020 - Present
Master of Mathematics - Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction), GPA: 96% - Thesis-based program [T1], resulting in an award-winning publication [C2].	Sept 2018 - Apr 2020
University of Calgary	Calgary, AB
Bachelor of Science - Computer Science, GPA: 96% - Graduated with First Class Honours (published paper [C1] plus high GPA).	Sept 2011 - Jun 2017
Bachelor of Commerce - Business Technology Management (BTMA), GPA: 96% - Winner: Haskayne School of Business Silver Medallion (highest graduating GPA in program).	Sept 2011 - Jun 2017

Work Experience

Meta Reality Labs	New York, NY
Research Scientist Intern, Input Explorations (mentors: Bruno de Araujo, Jota Costa)	Sept 2022 - Jan 2023

- Developed Unity prototypes of multimodal AR/VR interfaces using eye tracking and EMG.
- Designed and facilitated experiments to evaluate AR/VR eye tracking input accuracy.
- Analyzed and presented experiment results and high-level conclusions to stakeholders.

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA (Remote) Jun 2022 - Sept 2022

Research Intern, Ability Team (mentors: Martez Mott, Sasa Junuzovic, Edward Cutrell)

Primary author and developer on a VR accessibility research experiment involving multimodal VR input and 3D input remapping.

Research Intern, Ability Team (mentors: Martez Mott, Sasa Junuzovic, Edward Cutrell)

Primary author of an accessibility research publication [C3] using qualitative methods to investigate the use of multi-device input configurations by people with mobility limitations.

Autodesk Research Toronto, ON

Research Intern, UI Research Group (mentors: Fraser Anderson, Tovi Grossman)

- Primary author and sole Unity developer for a research paper on hybrid VR-desktop interfaces, resulting in a patent [P1] and conference publication [C4].
- Completed 4-month research project, including study data analysis and stakeholder presentation despite pandemic-related displacement and work-from-home transition.

May 2021 - Aug 2021

Jan 2020 - May 2020

New York University New York, NY

Visiting Scholar, Future Reality Lab (mentor: Ken Perlin)

Sept 2019 - Dec 2019

- Developed a simultaneous, multi-user augmented reality audio solution for an external client.
- Solo developer for a multiplayer iOS project using ARKit on iPhone and iPad.

Deloitte Calgary, AB

iOS/Web/AR Developer (Business Technology Analyst)

Aug 2017 - Aug 2018

- Created an iOS app for navigation and SAP Cloud interaction, implementing OCR functions and a custom keyboard UI.
- Created an AR eCommerce demo for industry clients using Unity, Vuforia, and Node.js.

Critical Mass Calgary, AB

User Experience Design Intern

May 2016-- Aug 2016

- Created interactive design prototypes for user testing, using code-based animation tools.
- Created and annotated user flows and wireframes for various websites and software.

University of Calgary

Calgary, AB Sept 2014 - Sept 2015

Undergraduate Researcher

- 3cpt 2014 3
- Developed an augmented reality interface between Google Glass, Kinect, and a Baxter humanoid robot.
- Published study findings as first author [C1], winning a Calgary Undergraduate Research Award.

SMART Technologies

Calgary, AB

User Experience Design Intern

May 2014 - Aug 2014

- Created automated data entry scripts to track and close user feature requests, reducing manual entry time by 50%.
- Created various full-process mockups for products, from concepts and sketches to videos and interactive prototypes.

Publications

Note about conference papers: In Human-Computer Interaction, conference proceedings are the preferred publication venue since they are timelier and typically have the greatest impact. Top-tier conferences are very selective with rigorous multi-stage reviews of full manuscripts creating high quality fully archival proceedings.

Note about venues: CHI (ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems) is recognized as a very top tier HCI conference (ranked #1 on Google Scholar). The average acceptance rate for CHI is 23%.

Peer-Reviewed Publications

- **Johann Wentzel**, Fraser Anderson, George Fitzmaurice, Tovi Grossman, Daniel Vogel. 2024. *SwitchSpace: Understanding Context-Aware Peeking Between VR and Desktop Interfaces*. To appear in Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '24).
- **Johann Wentzel**. 2023. *Bring-Your-Own Input: Context-Aware Multi-Modal Input for More Accessible Virtual Reality.* In Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstracts (CHI '23 Doctoral Consortium). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3544549.3577056
- Johann Wentzel and Lesley Istead. 2022. Volumetric and User-Centric Rendering Techniques for Lens Flare and Film Grain in Virtual Reality Environments. In the 2022 European Conference on Visual Media Production Extended Abstracts (CVMP '22). [PDF]
- Johann Wentzel, Sasa Junuzovic, James Devine, John Porter, Martez Mott. 2022. *Understanding How People with Limited Mobility Use Multi-Modal Input*. In Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '22). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3491102.3517458
- Johann Wentzel, Daekun Kim, and Jeremy Hartmann. 2021. Same Space, Different Place: Designing for Differing Physical Spaces in Social Virtual Reality. In the CHI 2021 workshop "Social VR: A New Medium for Communication and Collaboration". [More info | PDF]
- Josh Urban Davis, **Johann Wentzel**. 2021. Font Your Friends and Loved Ones: On the Utility of Ugly Interfaces. In Proceedings of the 2021 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems Extended Abstracts (CHI '21). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3411763.3450371

- Johann Wentzel, Greg d'Eon, and Daniel Vogel. 2020. Improving Virtual Reality Ergonomics through Reach-Bounded Non-Linear Input Amplification. In Proceedings of the CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3313831.3376687

 * Best Paper Honourable Mention (top 5% of submitted papers)
- **Johann Wentzel**, Daniel Rea, James Young, and Ehud Sharlin. 2015. *Shared Presence and Collaboration Using a Co-Located Humanoid Robot*. In Proceedings of the 3rd International Conference on Human-Agent Interaction (HAI '15). DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/2814940.2814995

Patents

[P1] **Johann Wentzel**, Fraser Anderson, Tovi Grossman, and George Fitzmaurice. *Transitions between states in a hybrid virtual reality desktop computing environment*. 2022. [Google Patents]

Theses and Dissertations

Johann Wentzel. 2020. Reach-Bounded, Non-Linear Input Amplification for More Comfortable Virtual Reality. Master's thesis, UWSpace. [Link]

Awards and Funding

2021-2024	Alexander Graham Bell Graduate Scholarship (NSERC CGS-D) (national) - \$105,000 over 3 years Awarded to top PhD students based on academic merit, research potential, and leadership.
2021-2024	President's Graduate Scholarship (institutional) - \$30,000 over 3 years Top-up funding awarded by University of Waterloo to winners of the NSERC CGS-D.
2021, 2020	Ontario Graduate Scholarship, PhD (provincial, declined for NSERC CGS-D) - \$15,000 Awarded to top PhD students based on academic excellence and research potential.
2020	Best Paper Honourable Mention (top 5% of submitted papers), CHI 2020 for [C2] "Improving Virtual Reality Ergonomics []" with Greg d'Eon and Daniel Vogel.
2020, 2018	President's Graduate Scholarship (institutional) - \$5,000 Top-up funding awarded by University of Waterloo to winners of provincial scholarships.
2019	Alexander Graham Bell Graduate Scholarship (NSERC CGS-M) (national) - \$17,500 National scholarship for top Master's students based on academics and research potential.
2019	Ontario Graduate Scholarship, Master's (provincial) - \$15,000 Provincial scholarship for top Master's students based on academic excellence and research potential.
2019	David Johnston International Experience Award (institutional) - \$2,500 Awarded to graduate students to support international work and study opportunities.
2018 - 2022	David R. Cheriton Graduate Scholarship (institutional) - \$20,000 over 2 years, won twice Awarded to top graduate students based on academic excellence and research potential.
2018	Domestic Masters Entrance Award (institutional) - \$5,000 Awarded to top incoming Master's students based on academic excellence.
2018	Alexander Graham Bell Graduate Scholarship (NSERC CGS-M) (national, declined) - \$17,500 Offered from University of Saskatchewan and Calgary, declined as I chose to attend Waterloo.
2017	Haskayne School of Business Silver Medallion in Business Technology Management Awarded to the Business Technology Management student with the highest graduating GPA.
2016	University of Calgary Undergraduate Merit Award (institutional) - \$800 Awarded to top continuing undergraduate students.
2015	Program for Undergraduate Research Experience Award (institutional) - \$6,000 Merit-based research funding for undergraduate students in the UCalgary Honours program.
2014	Alistair H. Ross Memorial Scholarship (institutional) - \$3,750 Awarded to top continuing undergraduate students based on GPA.
2011	President's Admission Scholarship (institutional) - \$2,500 Awarded to top incoming undergraduate students based on academic excellence.
2011-2017	Dean's List, University of Calgary Maintained a GPA above 3.6/4.0 while enrolled full-time in undergraduate studies.

Supervision

Daekun Kim, University of Waterloo undergraduate, Sept 2020 - Sept 2022

- "Exploring the effects of depth perception in virtual reality"

"Exploring the effects of hierarchy within 3D marking menus in virtual reality"

Invited Talks

- Conference Presentations: CHI 2022-2024, CHI 2020 (virtual), Waterloo CHI 2020 (virtual)
- Accessibility Strategies for using Extended Reality in Teaching. Educause 2023, Chicago, IL, USA
- Incorporating Emerging Technologies into Higher Education with Care: Accessibility Strategies for Virtual Reality and Augmented Reality. UWaterloo Teaching and Learning Conference 2023. Waterloo, ON, Canada.
- Breaking Into XR Research. UWaterloo VR Club. Waterloo, ON, Canada
- Robotics in Manufacturing / Working Alongside Baxter. ACAMP Seminar Series Unmanned Vehicles, Robotics, and Intelligent Systems Seminar. Calgary, AB, Canada.
- Shared Presence and Collaboration with a Co-Located Humanoid Robot. University of Calgary Undergraduate Research Symposium. Calgary, AB, Canada.

Press

School of Computer Science News, interview, 2023. PhD candidate Johann Wentzel makes virtual reality more accessible. https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/news/phd-candidate-iohann-wentzel-makes-virtual-reality-more-accessible

University of Waterloo News, interview, 2023, Waterloo doctoral candidate focuses on ways to make virtual reality more accessible. https://uwaterloo.ca/news/mathematics/virtual-reality-accessible

Government Technology, interview, 2022. What Is the Metaverse's Future in K-12 and Higher Ed? https://www.govtech.com/education/higher-ed/what-is-the-metaverses-future-in-k-12-and-higher-ed/what-is-the-metaverses-fut

Side Projects

HCIKit: An HCI Experiment Automation Framework

- A Unity framework for dynamically generating and counterbalancing HCl user studies.
- Allows for easy automation, replication, logging, and analysis of user study data.

Self-Configured Home Server

- A fully self-assembled home server for VPN, file hosting, smart home services, and multiplayer games.
- Configured using Proxmox and Docker, with incoming traffic routed via NGINX.

Service and Volunteering

Waterloo, ON Teaching

Instructional Apprentice, University of Waterloo

Leading computer labs as a lab instructor for undergraduate computer science courses.

Academic Service Waterloo, ON

Program Committee: ISS 2024, GI 2022

Session Chair: Waterloo CHI 2020 (online CHI event in response to COVID-19)

- Student Volunteer: UIST 2021, CHI 2021, UIST 2019
- Peer Reviewer: CHI, UIST, CHI PLAY, MobileHCI, ISS (all over several years)

Arts and Performance Calgary, AB

Actor/Musician - Calgary Community Theatre

Ongoing Cast member, orchestra performer, and technical setup advisor for various musical theatre productions in Calgary.

University of Calgary Orientation

Calgary, AB

Ongoing

Ongoing

Orientation Leader

Sept 2013 - Sept 2015

- Led large groups of incoming students on tours of campus, including one-on-one advice for campus life.
- Facilitated several campus-wide volunteering events to build awareness of University of Calgary services.

Skills

Programming Languages: C#, Swift, Python, R, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Objective-C, C++, SwiftUI Dev tools: Unity, Xcode, ARKit, RealityKit, Android Studio, Bootstrap, React, NumPy, ¡Query, NodeJS, Git.

Design tools: Figma, Sketch, Balsamig, Adobe Illustrator, Final Cut Pro

Hobbies: Home servers, game development for VR, AR, iOS. Classically trained in piano, clarinet, voice.